A Guide to The Papers of Judge Edward S. Smith, 1964-1997
University of Virginia, Arthur J. Morris Law Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Law Library
The Papers of Judge Edward S. Smith, 1964-1997
Special Collections, University of Virginia Law Library
MSS 01-3
Nine boxes
The papers of Judge Edward S. Smith consist primarily of papers regarding the administration of the court system.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
This collection was donated to the Law School Archives in August of 2001.
Biographical Information
Edward S. Smith was born in Birmingham, Alabama the 27 of March of 1919. He studied at the University of Virginia from where he received his B.A. in 1941 and LL.B /J.D. in 1947. He also studied at the Alabama Polytechnic Institute (now Auburn University) from 1936-1938 and received a major in Mechanical Engineering. In September of 1941 he entered active duty as Apprentice Seaman. He participated in the initial amphibious attacks in North Africa, Sicily, Normandy, Southern France and Okinawa. In 1944 he was Gunnery Officer of the U. S. S. Susan B. Anthony (AP-72) that was sunk off Normandy the 7 of June. Later he was First Lieutenant and Damage Control Officer, Executive Officer of U.S.S. Arcturus (AKA-1). He was released from the military on February of 1946 as a Lieutenant. He was active for 15 years in the Postwar Naval Reserve, in units concerned with industrial mobilization and armed services procurement contracts. He was member of the Naval Reserve Material Companies 5-2 and 5-3, 5th Naval District. He retired July 1st., 1968.
From 1947 to 1961 he was an associate and partner with the firm of Blair, Korner, Doyle, Worth and Crampton (this firm changed names). From 1961 he worked in the Tax Division of the U. S. Department of Justice as Chief of the Trial Section. There, he reorganized and administered several sections of the Tax Division and supervised civil refund litigation in all U. S. District Courts and the U. S. Courts of Claims. In 1962 and 1963 he served as deputy assistant attorney general for civil rights. From 1963 to 1977 he was partner in the law firm of Piper & Marbury Attorneys, in the city of Baltimore, where he was the head of the Tax and Estates Department. In 1978 was appointed to the U. S. Courts of Claims as an associate judge. From 1982-1989 he was judge of the U. S. Court of Appeals for the Federal Circuit; in 1989 he became senior circuit judge, and moved to Alabama where he continued to work until his death.
Judge Smith was member of the ABA; the Bar Association of the city of Baltimore; Baltimore Association of Tax Counsel; National Tax Association; Tax Institute of America; Federal Bar Association; District of Columbia Bar (1948, Tax Division); Virginia State Bar (1947); Bar Association of the District of Columbia (member of the Committee on U. S. Courts of Claims); and permanent member of the Judicial Conference of the Fourth Circuit. He was member of the Democratic Party. He taught as adjunct faculty at the University of Samford Law School and at the University of Alabama in Tuscaloosa.
Judge Edward S. Smith died March 22, 2001 in Birmingham, Alabama.
Scope and Content
This collection was donated to the Law School Archives in August of 2001 and it is organized in four parts:
Service on the United States Court of Claims Creation of the United States Courts of Appeals for the Federal Circuit Federal Circuit Administration Personal Papers
The collection reflects the administrative process that took place "to restructure a portion of the intermediate appellate tier". Judge Smith was appointed Judge of the Court of Claims in 1979. There were to many appeals and very few judges and it was a necessity to allow the reorganization. In 1978-1979, Daniel J. Meador Assistant Attorney General sent a proposal for restructuring the court system. This set of papers called the Meador Report began the process that concluded with the Federal Courts Improvement Act of 1979 and launched the necessary legislation to establish the United States Court of Appeals for the Federal Circuit. There are proposals, commentaries, discussions, hearings, statements, memoranda between judges. This collection can be an excellent source of information on how the courts work internally.
Arrangement
The papers are arranged in the following groups:
Service on U.S. Court of Claims: correspondence, letters of recommendation, memoranda between judges and personal notes regarding court of claims appointments and court administration rules, dating from primarily from 1977-1982. Boxes 1-2.
Creation of the U.S. Court of Appeals for the Federal District: Meador Report materials, dating from 1978 - 1991. Boxes 2-5.
Federal Circuit Administration: materials related to the Court of Appeals for the Federal Circuit, various surveys, reports, and rules regarding procedures, dating from 1976-1997. Boxes 6-8.
Personal: resume, published articles, letters, speeches, class notes and working materials, dating from 1964-1985. Box 9.
Contents List
- Service on U. S. Court of Claims
  - [Court Administration] Rules. [Memoranda between Judges, Notes] 1978-1980 (Box 1)
  - [Court Appointment File]. Correspondence, Letters of Recommendation 1977-1978 (Box 1)
  - [Court of Claims Appointment] Correspondence and personal notes 1977-1978, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Court of Claims Building 1965-1969, 1979, 1988 (Box 1)
  - Indian Cases [Attorneys Fees] 1978-1979 (Box 1)
  - Report re Court of Claims by Management Review Division. Administrative Office 1981 (Box 2)
  - Spector-Goddard Controversy 1981 (Box 2)
  - Trial Judge George Willi Case 1976-1980, 1982 (Box 2)
- Creation of the U. S. Court of Appeals for the Federal District
  - Meador Report [A proposal to improve the Federal Appellate System] 1978, July (Box 2)
  - Meador Report - S. 677 and S. 678. [ Early Proposals for new United States Court of Appeals for the Federal Circuit and Correspondence] 1978-1979, 5 folders (Box 2-3)
  - Meador Report [Statements of Donald C. Alexander, Mortimer Caplin, Howard T. Markey, Stuart E. Siegel, Daniel M. Friedman] 1979, May (Box 3)
  - Meador Report Publicity 1978-1979 (Box 3)
  - S. 677 Judicial Improvement Act of 1979 1979, March 15 (Box 3)
  - S. 678 Federal Courts Improvement Act of 1979 1979, March 15 (Box 3)
  - [S. 1477 - Federal Courts Improvement Act of 1979. Memoranda between Judges] 1979, 3 folders (Box 3-4)
  - [S.1691 To provide Improvements in the Structure and Administration of the Federal Tax Courts...] 1979, Aug. (Box 4)
  - [H. R. 3806 - Court of Appeals for the Federal Circuit Act of 1980] 1980, Feb. - Apr., 3 folders (Box 4)
  - [S. 21 & H. R. 2405: Memoranda, Testimonies] 1980, Dec. 1981, March, 2 folders (Box 4-5)
  - Legislation re Federal Courts (Miscellaneous) 1977-1978, 1981, 1988-1991 (Box 5)
- Federal Circuit Administration
  - [Copies of Statutory Materials Related to the Court of Appeals for the Federal Circuit] 1982, 3 folders (Box 5)
  - Grassley Survey (for Senate Judicial Committee) on Court Workload 1996-1997, 2 folders (Box 6)
  - [Internal Rules and Procedures Discussed by Judges] 1981-1982 (Box 6)
  - Judicial Conference Committee on the Judicial Branch 1980-1986 (Box 6)
  - Memoranda re Miscellaneous Cases from Judge Smith 1980-1989 (Box 6)
  - [Miscellaneous Court Administration Matters] 1976-1984, 1990, 2 folders (Box 7)
  - Seminar for Newly Appointed Federal Appellate Judges 1982 (Box 7)
  - U. S. Courts of Appeals for the Federal Circuit Rules 1981-1982, 2 folders (Box 7)
  - U. S. Courts of Appeals for the Federal Circuit Tenth Anniversary Program 1992, Oct. 1 (Box 7)
  - "State of the Court" Summer Letters 1983-1987 (Box 7)
  - "White Commission" or Commission on Structural Alternatives for the Federal Court of Appeals 1989, 4 folders (Box 8)
- Personal
  - [Court Claims Appointment]; Personnel File: Resume and Published Articles, etc. 1977 (Box 9)
  - Judge Smith. Information re Appointment. 1978-1985 (Box 9)
  - Smith Speeches 1979-1988 (Box 9)
  - [Class Notes?, Working Materials? Probably related to Judge Smith and Scott P. Crampton] 1964-1969 (Box 9)
- Correspondence List
  - Richard H. Appert, Esq. New York, New York
  - S. Eason Balch, Esq. Birmingham, Alabama
  - S. Eason Balch, Esq. Birmingham, Alabama
  - John S. Battle Richmond, Virginia
  - William C. Battle President of Field Crest Mills, Inc. Eden, N. C.
  - Alexis I. du Pont Bayard, Esq. Wilmington, Delaware
  - Senator Birch Bayh Washington, D. C.
  - George Beall, Esq. Baltimore, Maryland
  - Giora Ben-Horin, Esq. Phoenix, Arizona
  - Edward B. Benjamin, Jr., Esq. New Orleans, Louisiana
  - Senator Joseph R. Biden, Jr. Washington, D. C.
  - John M. Bray, Esq. Washington, D. C.
  - Mortimer Caplin, Esq. Washington, D. C.
  - Gene A. Castleberry, Esq. Oklahoma City, Oklahoma
  - Calvin H. Cobb, Esq. Washington, D. C.
  - Sheldon S. Cohen, Esq. Washington, D. C.
  - Scott P. Crampton, Esq. Washington, D. C.
  - Barbara B. Creed, Esq. San Francisco, California
  - Eugene G. Eason, Esq. C/o Steptoe & Johnson Clarksburg, West Virginia
  - E. Charles Eichenbaum, Esq. Little Rock, Arkansas
  - H. Vernon Eney, Esq. Baltimore, Maryland
  - Hon. M. Carr Ferguson Tax Division, U. S. Dept of Justice Washington, D. C.
  - Marvin Joseph Garbis, Esq. Baltimore, Maryland
  - Charles W. Hall Houston, Texas
  - John H. Hall, Esq. Los Angeles, California
  - Don V. Harris, Esq. Washington, D. C.
  - Isaac Hecht, Esq. Baltimore, Maryland
  - F. Cleveland Hedrick, Jr. Washington, D. C.
  - Lee H. Henkel, Jr., Esq. Atlanta, Georgia
  - Vester T. Hughes, Jr. Esq. Dallas, Texas
  - Henry C. Ikenberry, Esq. Washington, D. C.
  - Hon. Philip C. Jackson, Jr. Washington, D. C.
  - Julian I. Jacobs, Esq. Baltimore, Maryland
  - Bruce H. Johnson, Esq. Oklahoma City, Oklahoma
  - John B. Jones, Esq. Washington, D. C.
  - Senator. Edward M. Kennedy Washington, D. C.
  - William L. Kinzer, Esq. Atlanta, Georgia
  - Jules G. Korner, III Washington, D. C.
  - Hover T. Lenz, Esq. Denver, Colorado
  - Warren V. Ludlam, Esq. Jackson, Mississippi
  - Charles C. MacLean, Esq. New York, New York
  - William D. McLean, Esq. Rockville, Maryland
  - Senator Charles Mc C. Mathias, Jr. Washington, D. C.
  - Donald L. McCaskey, Esq. Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania
  - Robert P. Mittelman, Esq. Baltimore, Maryland
  - Stanley C. Morris, Jr. Washington, D. C.
  - Senator Sam Nunn Washington, D. C.
  - Hon. Louis F. Oberdorfer McLean, Virginia
  - John S. Pennell, Esq. Chicago, Ill.
  - John T. Piper Bogle & Gates Seattle, Washington
  - Lester M. Ponder, Esq. Indianapolis, Indiana
  - C. Frank Reifsnyder, Esq. Washington, D. C.
  - Mitchell Rogovin, Esq. Washington, D. C.
  - Alan F. Rothschild, Esq. Columbus, Georgia
  - Michael C. Russ, Esq. Atlanta, Georgia
  - Frank P. Samford, Jr., Esq. Birmingham, Alabama
  - Hon. Barefoot Sanders, Jr., Esq. Dallas, Texas
  - Jacques T. Schlenger, Esq. Baltimore, Maryland
  - Esward J. Schmuck, Esq. Washington, D. C.
  - Bernard G. Segal, Esq. Philadelphia, Pennsylvania
  - Sargent Shriver, Esq. Washington, D. C.
  - Sherwin P. Simmons, Esq. Trebam, Simmons, Kemper, Scharf, Barkin, Frye & O'Neill Tampa, Florida
  - George A. Smathers, Esq. Washington, D. C.
  - Gary P. Smith, Esq. Birmingham, Alabama
  - Senator John Sparkman Washington, D. C.
  - Hart H. Spiegel, Esq. San Francisco, California
  - Norman A. Sugarman, Esq. Washington, D. C.
  - William A. Sutherland, Esq. Sutherland, Asbill & Brennan Washington, D. C.
  - Senator Herman E. Talmadge Washington, D. C.
  - S. Shepherd Tate, Esq. Memphis, Tennessee
  - Joseph D. Tydings, Esq. Washington, D. C.
  - William Waller, Esq. Nashville, Tennessee
  - Johnie M. Walters, Esq. Washington, D. C.
  - Meade Whitaker, Esq. Washington, D. C.
  - W. Bew White, Jr., Esq. Birmingham, Alabama
  - Stanley H. Wilen, Esq. Baltimore, Maryland
  - Glen A. Wilkinson, Esq. Washington, D. C.
  - Elliott T. Williams, Esq. Birmingham, Alabama
  - Andrew B. Young, Esq. Philadelphia, Pennsylvania